<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>security on Human and Machine Learning in Cognitive Science</title><link>tylerjamesmalloy.github.io/tags/security/</link><description>Recent content in security on Human and Machine Learning in Cognitive Science</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><copyright>&lt;a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">CC BY-NC 4.0&lt;/a></copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 16 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="tylerjamesmalloy.github.io/tags/security/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Security and Human Behaviour 2023</title><link>tylerjamesmalloy.github.io/posts/shb-2023/</link><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>tylerjamesmalloy.github.io/posts/shb-2023/</guid><description>The following are my notes taken during the SHB workshop. I have included the names of presenters but it should be noted that these are my own general thoughs and reactions while attending these presentations, and not necessarily the views and opinions of the presenters.
Session 1: Privacy Lorrie Cranor: Designing Visable and Useful Privacy Icons: Privacy &amp;rsquo;nutrition labels&amp;rsquo; can be used to inform the public on their privacy concerns. 2020: App security labels tested, many instances of confusion from participants.</description></item><item><title>Job Security</title><link>tylerjamesmalloy.github.io/posts/job-security/</link><pubDate>Wed, 05 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>tylerjamesmalloy.github.io/posts/job-security/</guid><description>I recently completed the last meeting with a small group of mentees from my alma mater UBC that was put together to give undergraduate students at different points in their career some insight into life after undergrad. I think it was a great experience for myself, as I had little previous work as a direct mentor, and hopefully the mentees felt the same way. The remainder of this blog post is some reflections from my experience as a mentor and the life lessons I have thought of and tried to discuss with them.</description></item></channel></rss>