<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>papers on Human and Machine Learning in Cognitive Science</title><link>tylerjamesmalloy.github.io/tags/papers/</link><description>Recent content in papers on Human and Machine Learning in Cognitive Science</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>&lt;a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">CC BY-NC 4.0&lt;/a></copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 28 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="tylerjamesmalloy.github.io/tags/papers/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Masters Thesis 2020</title><link>tylerjamesmalloy.github.io/posts/masters-thesis-2020/</link><pubDate>Tue, 28 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>tylerjamesmalloy.github.io/posts/masters-thesis-2020/</guid><description>This post is another retrospective, but instead of a conference or journal paper it takes a look at my masters thesis, titled &amp;ldquo;Modelling Learning and Decision Making Under Information Processing Constraints&amp;rdquo;. This blog post will go through the begninning stages of the project and how it ultimately narrowed down the focus of the thesis and project into what it eventually became.
Very early on in my PhD, I became interested my advisor Chris Sims&amp;rsquo; previous work using infromation theory, specifically mutual information, as a tool to understand the cognitive costs of behaviour in learning and decision making tasks.</description></item><item><title>Predicting Human Choice</title><link>tylerjamesmalloy.github.io/posts/predicting-human-choice/</link><pubDate>Wed, 15 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>tylerjamesmalloy.github.io/posts/predicting-human-choice/</guid><description>This is the first post in a series of retrospectives looking back at papers and conferences I have attended. Now that I am entering my final year of my PhD, I will be begining this as a chronicle of projects, papers and conferences that influenced my time during my PhD.
This was my first accepted paper, I submitted it to the conference Reinforcement Learning and Decision Making in 2019. I attended the conference which was a great experience.</description></item></channel></rss>