<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Papers on Human and Machine Learning in Cognitive Science</title><link>tylerjamesmalloy.github.io/tags/papers/</link><description>Recent content in Papers on Human and Machine Learning in Cognitive Science</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en</language><copyright>&lt;a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">CC BY-NC 4.0&lt;/a></copyright><lastBuildDate>Mon, 05 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="tylerjamesmalloy.github.io/tags/papers/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>NeurIPS 2022</title><link>tylerjamesmalloy.github.io/posts/neurips-2022/</link><pubDate>Mon, 05 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>tylerjamesmalloy.github.io/posts/neurips-2022/</guid><description>This year I attended the Conference on Neural Information Processing Systems for the first time to present a poster alongside a paper that was accepted at the workshop on Information Theoretic Principles in Cognitive Systems.
The first day fo the conference I attended the NewInML workshop, which was intended for researchers that are new to the machine learning community. Since this was my first NeurIPS and my background is in cognitive science, this felt like the perfect way to start the conference.</description></item><item><title>Masters Thesis 2020</title><link>tylerjamesmalloy.github.io/posts/masters-thesis-2020/</link><pubDate>Tue, 28 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>tylerjamesmalloy.github.io/posts/masters-thesis-2020/</guid><description>This post is another retrospective, but instead of a conference or journal paper it takes a look at my masters thesis, titled &amp;ldquo;Modelling Learning and Decision Making Under Information Processing Constraints&amp;rdquo;. This blog post will go through the begninning stages of the project and how it ultimately narrowed down the focus of the thesis and project into what it eventually became.
Very early on in my PhD, I became interested my advisor Chris Sims&amp;rsquo; previous work using infromation theory, specifically mutual information, as a tool to understand the cognitive costs of behaviour in learning and decision making tasks.</description></item><item><title>AAAI 2021</title><link>tylerjamesmalloy.github.io/posts/aaai-2021/</link><pubDate>Sun, 26 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>tylerjamesmalloy.github.io/posts/aaai-2021/</guid><description>This is the second post in a series of retrospectives on previous work I have done that shaped my PhD and are related to my future research goals. If you would like to read the paper you can find it on my Researchgate.
Although this paper is relatively recent, I thought I would use it as my second post because it is closely realted to a project that I began soon after beginning my AI Researcher position with IBM in early 2019.</description></item><item><title>Predicting Human Choice</title><link>tylerjamesmalloy.github.io/posts/predicting-human-choice/</link><pubDate>Wed, 15 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>tylerjamesmalloy.github.io/posts/predicting-human-choice/</guid><description>This is the first post in a series of retrospectives looking back at papers and conferences I have attended. Now that I am entering my final year of my PhD, I will be begining this as a chronicle of projects, papers and conferences that influenced my time during my PhD.
This was my first accepted paper, I submitted it to the conference Reinforcement Learning and Decision Making in 2019. I attended the conference which was a great experience.</description></item></channel></rss>