<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Presentation on Human and Machine Learning in Cognitive Science</title><link>tylerjamesmalloy.github.io/tags/presentation/</link><description>Recent content in Presentation on Human and Machine Learning in Cognitive Science</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en</language><copyright>&lt;a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">CC BY-NC 4.0&lt;/a></copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 14 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="tylerjamesmalloy.github.io/tags/presentation/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Narrowing The Gap With LLMs</title><link>tylerjamesmalloy.github.io/posts/narrowing-gap/</link><pubDate>Tue, 14 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>tylerjamesmalloy.github.io/posts/narrowing-gap/</guid><description>This will be my third blog post in a row (see the first, and second) on the topic of large language models. While this area of research has been in the news significantly recently, it is not exactly my area. However, there was a talk at the University of Pittsburgh philosophy department given by professor Colin Allen that was, at least partially, presented as a refutation to the position of David Chalmers that I discussed previously.</description></item><item><title>PhD Defense</title><link>tylerjamesmalloy.github.io/posts/phd-defense/</link><pubDate>Thu, 10 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>tylerjamesmalloy.github.io/posts/phd-defense/</guid><description>It has been a while since I made a blog post, mostly becase I have been working hard on my PhD Dissertation and practicing for my defense, which you can watch a practice run through of at this link. Since the last time I made a post I have defended my dissertation and I am now in the final stages of my work at Rensselaer. I have had an amazing time working at RPI with my mentor Chris R.</description></item><item><title>Vss 2022</title><link>tylerjamesmalloy.github.io/posts/vss-2022/</link><pubDate>Sat, 28 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>tylerjamesmalloy.github.io/posts/vss-2022/</guid><description>Earlier this month I attented the Visual Science Society 2022 conference where I gave a talk titled &amp;ldquo;A Beta-Variational Auto-Encoder Model of Human Visual Representation Formation in Utility-Based Learning&amp;rdquo;. The entire abstract I submitted is copied at the bottom of this blog post if you would like to read it.
The VSS experience was very positive, I was somewhat worried or hesitant that I would not get a lot of the posters and talks since my experience is much more in the learning domain rather than vision.</description></item></channel></rss>